<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good newes from Oxford (of the treaty) for the surrender thereof: and how they are packing up to march away on Thursday next, June 18. 1646. With the surrender of Sherburne-house already agreed. Also the particulars of the seven visions seene at Gravenhage the 31. of May last; translated out of the Dutch copies. Printed by the originall papers and published according to order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E340_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200885</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861510</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861510</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E340[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good newes from Oxford (of the treaty) for the surrender thereof: and how they are packing up to march away on Thursday next, June 18. 1646. With the surrender of Sherburne-house already agreed. Also the particulars of the seven visions seene at Gravenhage the 31. of May last; translated out of the Dutch copies. Printed by the originall papers and published according to order.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Jane Coe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An early copy in my possession has 'Gravenadge' in the title--Madan.</note>
                  <note>Verso of last leaf has a "rude engraving .. apparently of the siege of York, .. it had been used before for 'Ruperts sumpter' published in July, 1644"--Madan. Illustration has caption: Pack up and away from Oxford.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apparitions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Treaties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oxford (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Good Newes from OXFORD <hi>(Of the TREATY)</hi> For the Surrender thereof: And how they are packing up to march away on Thurſday next, <hi>June</hi> 18. 1646.</p>
            <p>WITH <hi>The Surrender of</hi> Sherburne-houſe <hi>already agreed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO</hi> The particulars of the ſeven Viſions ſeene at <hi>Gravenhage</hi> the 31. of <hi>May</hi> laſt; Tranſlated out of the Dutch Copies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by the Originall Papers, and publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Jane Coe,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="summary_of_letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:159746:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159746:2"/>
            <head>AN Abſtract of the Letters From the leager before OXFORD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wonderfull workes of GOD have and doe ſtill appeare for that godly and valiant Army with Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> in the ſo farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of this Kingdome to peace, in which God hath made his Excellencie a glorious Inſtrument.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159746:3"/>
            <p> And now ſince his Excellency came before <hi>Oxford,</hi> that work hath been carryed on with very great diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and although we have ſtill gone on with the work in preparing to ſtorme, and approaches made very neere to the enemy in ſeverall places about the City, yet the Treaty hath ſtill gone on, and the Enemy been every day more and more daunted and diſcouraged from reſiſting us, though the moſt pernitious neſt in the Kingdome, and a place the moſt impregnable of any, and the perſons deſperate.</p>
            <p>We have now gone through divers of the Articles, and (though with much difficulty) come neere to the end; but to God is all the praiſe to be given for this great work, for it could not be any wayes expected from the arme of fleſh, eſpecially from ſuch a poore deſpiſed Army as that was at the firſt: but to the Lord be the glory of his owne works.</p>
            <p>For the buſineſſe of the Treaty for the ſurrender of <hi>Oxford,</hi>i t is certified thus: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Commiſſioners ſate late on Saterday, <hi>June</hi> 13, and have overcome all difficulties in the Treaty, there being onely circumſtantiall things to be concluded on, which at the next meeting without peradventure will be finiſhed: ſo that by Thurſday next it is conceived they will march out of <hi>Oxford;</hi> they are already packing up in <hi>Oxford</hi> in preparation towards their march. His Excellencie upon a ſecond humble Petition from Miſtreſſe <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> of Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne hath accepted of the ſurrender of Sherburne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159746:3"/>houſe in Oxfordſhire; The Generall upon her firſt Petition adviſed her to addreſſe her ſelfe to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which it ſeemes ſhe did; but by reaſon of other great affaires, obtained no poſitive Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Although the Houſe hath been a Garriſon, yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at our firſt comming to Oxford this time twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>month, nor all this while we have been here hath any wayes annoyed our Forces, but on the contrary hath contributed in proviſions to the maintenance of thoſe Forces imployed about Wallingford, as other parts have done. This houſe being kept with ſome men and Armes in it by Maſter <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> prevented the making of the ſame an active Gartiſon for the King, which would much have annoyed <hi>Henly</hi> and thoſe parts: And have onely ſtood upon their Guards to defend themſelves from Plunder, and never took any of the Parliaments Soldiers Priſoners, nor offered vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence unto them, nor raiſed Contribution of the Countrey. If this be the Gaſe, (as they alledge it to be) it is different from any other in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Enemy made a ſally out of <hi>Farringdon</hi> with Clubs, but were beaten in, two of their Horſes killed, and three men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account_of_a_vision">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159746:4"/>
            <head>A ſight ſeene in Gravenhage the 31. of May 1646. Jn the light of mid-day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 12. and 1. of the Clock:</head>
            <p n="1">I.<lb/> Happened a round plate about the bigneſſe of a Table-board, like gray paper without which appeared a Lyon, and a Dragon, which fought very fiercly one againſt another, which Dragon alſo ſpat fire; then was overcome by the Lyon, and ſo vaniſhed, but the Lyon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſight.</p>
            <p n="2">II.<lb/> There appeared by the Lyon, a multitude of Souldiers; as well Foote as Horſe, and before each Troope a Trumpeter, which men might perfectly ſee them put their Trumpets to their mouthes, and then ſee troopes begin to fight one againſt another, that men knew not who had the better, and the people vaniſhed, but the Lyon and the Dragon appeare ſtill in ſight.</p>
            <p n="3">III.<lb/> There appeared then a King with 3. Crownes upon his head, ſitting upon a Kingly throne, with people about his Throne, and vaniſhed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159746:4"/>ſtraight, then the Lyon and the Dragon ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſight.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII.<lb/> There appeared a multitude of mens heads, with a great head under them, and a multitude of bodies without heads, the which alſo vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then the Lyon and the Dragon remaine as before ſtanding in ſight</p>
            <p n="5">V.<lb/> There appeared alſo a man fitting upon a horſe who kills himſelfe and fallsbackward.</p>
            <p n="6">VI.<lb/> There alſo appeared a mighty Fleet of Ships in the South-weſt, and drive to the South-eaſt by the Lyon and the Dragon, when the fight was with multitudes of men upon the Ships, and men ſaw them preſently, to hould the Sails, and ſo drive one by another, then they appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all to ſtand, and the Lyon and the Dragon deſtroy one another, and fall backward, and then vaniſhed.</p>
            <p n="7">VII.<lb/> Then there remaines a great Cloud, which before was not, and ſo drave forward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the winde.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
